Finding aid for American Citizens for Justice Records, 1983-2004
Bentley Historical Library
American Citizens for Justice Records
1983-2004
Bentley Historical Library
American Citizens for Justice.
05100 Bd 2
9 linear feet
7 digital audiovisual files
The American Citizens for Justice, (or the Asian American Center for Justice) a Detroit-based Asian American civil rights group, was founded in reaction to the fatal beating of Vincent Chin, a Chinese-American man. The ACJ later evolved into an organization advocating for the rights of Asian-Americans in general. Records consist of meeting minutes, financial reports, correspondence, publications and grants, Vincent Chin related information, legal case files, health project files, as well as topical files.
The records were deposited by the American Citizens for Justice (donor no. 9614 ) in June 2005. Additions to the collection deposited in October 2005
The record group is open to research.
The American Citizens for Justice (or the Asian American Center for Justice), a Detroit-based Asian American civil rights group was founded in reaction to the fatal beating of Vincent Chin, a Chinese-American man. On June 19, 1982, while at a club in Detroit for his bachelor party, Chin encountered Ronald Ebens, a Detroit autoworker. According to reports, Ebens verbally harassed Chin, blaming his race for recent U.S. automotive unemployment (mistakenly believing Chin to be Japanese). A fight between the two men broke out, Chin striking Ebens before the men were separated. Ebens and his stepson, Michael Nitz, later deliberately tracked down Chin and attacked him with a baseball bat in front of a fast-food restaurant. Injuries from the attack led to Chin's death four days later.
Outraged by a judge's lenient sentence for these two men: a $3000 fine and 3 years probation, a group of Asian Pacific Americans formed the American Citizens for Justice on March 30, 1983, with the immediate goal of fighting for a retrial. Consisting of individuals of wide-ranging Asian descent including Chinese, Japanese, Korean, and Filipino, this group represented for the "first time, according to APA advocates and academics, that people who trace their ancestry to different countries in Asia and the Pacific Islands crossed ethnic and socioeconomic lines to fight as a united group of Asian Pacific Americans" (http://www.asianweek.com/061397/feature.html, para. 9). Working with other Asian Pacific American groups, the ACJ gathered support, "staged rallies, organized demonstrations, and launched a massive letter-writing campaign" (para. 23) all in hopes of bringing Chin's killers to justice. In 1984, the two men were brought to trial and Ebens was found guilty and sentenced to 25 years in prison. However, this ruling was later overturned due to a legal technicality. In a 1987 retrial, Ebens and Nitz were found not guilty on all charges.
The goals of the American Citizens for Justice have extended since the Chin incident, moving beyond the trial to broader aims of educating the public about Asian-American discrimination and helping other victims of racial harassment and injustice. The ACJ advocates for Asian-Pacific Americans in several areas, including law enforcement, legislation, networking, education, and health (ACJ brochure). In addition to offering free legal consultation to victims of racial harassment and discrimination, the ACJ also collaborates with other attorneys and legal groups to monitor and provide advice for anti-Asian incidents throughout the country. Through petitions and letter-writing, the ACJ "works to influence public policy and public institutions for just treatment of APAs" (ACJ brochure). Additionally, the ACJ has been fully involved in public education, sponsoring several workshops and conferences, educating students and others on Asian-American discrimination and culture. Throughout its existence, the ACJ has also been involved in many different projects. In 1989, with a grant from the Michigan Department of Public Health, the ACJ conducted a health needs assessment survey of the Southeast Asian communities of Detroit. The ACJ is still in existence today and continues to advocate for Asian Americans.
The American Citizens for Justice record group details the administrative functions as well as the activities and goals of the organization. Records consist of meeting minutes, financial reports, correspondence, publications and grants, Vincent Chin related information, legal case files, health project files, as well as topical files.
This Record group contains the following series: Administrative, Vincent Chin Case and Aftermath, Public Relations, Grants/Funding, Activities, Topical, and Visual Materials.
Asian Americans -- Michigan.; Asian Americans -- Michigan.; Chinese Americans -- Michigan.; Chinese Americans -- Michigan.; Minorities -- Crimes against -- Michigan.; Digital file formats.; Photographs.; Video recordings.; American Citizens for Justice.; Chin, Vincent.; American Citizens for Justice.
- Administrative, 1982-2003; 3 linear feet
  The Administrative series (3 linear feet, 1982-2003) details the overall governing and planning structure of the ACJ including constitution and bylaws, executive board meeting minutes and agenda, financial reports and statements, incoming correspondence (1984-2003) and some outgoing correspondence (1988-1990). Meeting minutes and director's reports are especially useful for the background and planning of ACJ projects and to get an overall sense of the ACJ's goals.
  - Constitution and by-laws (Box 1)
  - Executive Director
    - David Fukuzawa (Box 1)
    - Joanna Su (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1988-1990; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Executive Board
    - Forms and procedures (Box 1)
    - Meeting minutes/agenda, 1985-2003; 21 folders (Box 1)
    - Retreats (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Attorney (Box 2)
    - Finance (Box 2)
    - Fundraising (Box 2)
    - Strategic planning (Box 2)
  - Membership
    - Membership form (Box 2)
    - Membership lists (Box 2)
    - General meetings, 1982-1985; 1987-1999; 14 folders
      - Future speakers (Box 2)
  - Finance
    - Financial statements, 1987-1994 (Box 2)
    - Fundraising (Box 2)
    - Market plan, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Treasurer's reports
      - 1987 (Box 2)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 2)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 2)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming
      - 1984-1985, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
      - 1989 (Box 2)
      - 1990 (Box 2)
      - 1991 (Box 2)
      - 1992 (Box 2)
      - 1993 (Box 2)
      - 1994 (Box 2)
      - 1995 (Box 3)
      - 1996 (Box 3)
      - 1997 (Box 3)
      - 1998 (Box 3)
      - 1999 (Box 3)
      - 2000 (Box 3)
      - 2001 (Box 3)
      - 2002 (Box 3)
      - 2003, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Outgoing, 1988-1990; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Other
    - Miscellaneous and agendas (Box 3)
    - Rededication programs, 1983; 1985-1999; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Status report, 1989 (Box 3)
- Vincent Chin Case and Aftermath, 1983-1989; 0.5 linear feet
  The Vincent Chin Case and Aftermath series (0.5 linear feet, 1983-1989) contains files relating to the Vincent Chin incident and legal case, including clippings and articles, ACJ's involvement with the case (court watch documents, petitions, remembrance services), as well as public reaction, including response letters from viewers of a Phil Donahue show that covered the Chin case in 1983.
  - General information
    - Scrapbook of articles and information on Vincent Chin, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Articles and clippings, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - ACJ organizing efforts, 1983-1986 (Box 4)
    - Donations, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Film, "Who killed Vincent Chin?", 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Other group involvement/reactions, 1983-1984; 1987 (Box 4)
    - Remembrance services, 1983-1989 (Box 4)
    - Remembrance services, ACJ/Hawaii day of remembrance, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Response letters from Phil Donahue show, 1983; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Run for Justice, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Court case
    - Articles on court ruling, 1983-1987; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Court watch documents and copies of legal documents, 1983-1984; 1987 (Box 4)
    - Ebens, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - Letters from ACJ re: Chin case, 1983; 1985; 1989 (Box 4)
    - Chin case petition forms, ca., 1983 (Box 4)
- Public Relations, 1983-2001; 0.3 linear feet
  The Public Relations series (0.3 linear feet 1983-2001) includes informational brochures and flyers, press releases, speeches, and newsletters.
  - Contact lists, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Flyers/brochures, 1988-1997 (Box 4)
  - General PR, 1987-1988; undated (Box 4)
  - Press releases, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Speeches, 1983-1991 (Box 4)
  - Support documents (Box 4)
  - Publications
    - Newsletters
      - Justice Update, 1983-2001
        - 1983-1997, 15 folders (Box 4)
        - 1998-1999, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - 2001 (Box 5)
    - Year book, 1983 (Box 5)
- Grants/Funding, 1984-2001; 0.75 linear feet
  The Grants/Funding series (0.75 linear feet, 1984-2001) contains ACJ grant proposals submitted to various agencies and foundations (arranged by organization). The proposals are especially useful for information on the background of the ACJ as well as the proposed activities and projects of the organization as well.
  - Contacts and funding summaries, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Proposals, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Grants, 1992; 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - ACJ recipe book, 1988 (Box 5)
  - ANR Pipeline Company, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Bingo files, 1991 (Box 5)
  - The Boehm Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Buck Dinner, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Bydale Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Chicago Resource Center, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Chrysler Motors, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Coalition for Human Needs, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Community Foundation for Southeastern Michigan, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Deer Creek Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Donovan, Leisure, Newton & Irvine Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Episcopal Diocese of Michigan, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church in America, 1988 (Box 5)
  - The Field Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - First of America Bank Fund, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Ford Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Ford Motor Company, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Funding Exchange/National Community Funds, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - General Motors Foundation, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Hughes Memorial Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Hycliff Foundation, Inc., 1988 (Box 5)
  - Inacomp Computers, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - J. Roderick MacArthur Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Japan Business Society of Detroit Foundation, 1995-2001; 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Joint Foundation Support, 1989 (Box 5)
  - McGregor Fund, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Bell Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Council for the Humanities, 1988 (Box 5)
  - The Needmor Fund, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Norman Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - The Ottinger Foundation, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Presbyterian USA Funding, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Sisters of the Living Word, 1988 (Box 5)
  - United Foundation, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - United Methodist Church, 1987-1990; 4 folders (Box 5)
- Activities, 1985-2004; 3.25 linear feet
  The Activities series (3.25 linear feet, 1985-2004) comprises all of the various activities of the ACJ and has been divided into several subseries: education, health, legal, and other.
  - Education
    The Education subseries documents the ACJ's involvement in public education of Asian Pacific Americans, covering issues like discrimination as well as history and culture through conferences and workshops. Many of the files contain handouts and agendas from these various events.
    - General
      - Asian American Civil Rights Education project, 1988-89 (Box 5)
      - Media project (Box 5)
    - Workshops/conferences
      - ACJ Youth Conference
        - May 20, 1995 (Box 5)
        - September 23, 1995 (Box 5)
        - September 13, 1997 (Box 5)
      - Cultural Awareness workshop, 1998 (Box 5)
      - "Enhancing Police and Community Trust,", 2000 (Box 5)
      - Multicultural Immersion Program, 1996-2004; 9 folders (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Health, 1989-1990
    The Health subseries contains files relating to the ACJ's involvement in health-related issues. Most of the documents pertain to ACJ's 1989/1990 Southeast Asian Community Health Needs Assessment Project, funded by the Michigan Department of Health.
    - Topical files
      - AMAP (Asian Mutual Assistance Program) (Box 6)
      - Mental Health Needs and Services for Asian Americans project (Box 6)
      - MDHEC (Metropolitan Detroit Health Education Council) Conference (Box 6)
      - Minority Health Issues Committee (Box 6)
      - Minority HIV RFP (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous health-related documents (Box 6)
      - Reduction in mortality/morbidity in minorities RFP (Box 6)
      - Refugee Act, 1980 (Box 6)
      - United Community Services (Box 6)
    - Southeast Asian Community Health Needs Assessment Project
      - Background/research
        - Community survey (Box 6)
        - Detroit Health Department (Box 6)
        - Health provider survey questionnaires (Box 6)
        - Health surveys (Box 6)
        - Hmong community (Box 6)
        - Laotian community (Box 6)
        - Multicultural clinics (Box 6)
        - Other minority health projects (Box 6)
        - Refugee health (Box 6)
        - Refugee mental health (Box 6)
        - Refugee mutual assistance associations (Box 6)
        - Refugees in Michigan (Box 6)
        - Southeast Asians, resources (Box 6)
      - Project
        - Contact notes (Box 6)
        - Financial status reports (Box 6)
        - Health provider survey questionnaire (Box 6)
        - Health Task Force (Box 6)
        - Interview materials (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous proposals and notes (Box 6)
        - Proposals and budgets (Box 6)
        - Proposals and planning (Box 6)
        - Reports (Box 6)
        - Status reports (Box 6)
        - Survey logistics (Box 6)
        - Survey publications (Box 6)
  - Legal
    The Legal subseries contains case files of ACJ clients as well as documents and correspondence referring to regional and national legal cases that the ACJ followed.
    - Attorney client committee intake form (Box 7)
    - Attorney watch for anti-Asian incidents, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Civil rights project (Box 7)
    - ACJ case files, 1989-1990
      - Brown, X. (discrimination INS) (Box 7)
      - Chou, S. (employment) (Box 7)
      - Chow, C. (racial harassment and false accusation) (Box 7)
      - Dick, M. (traffic incident) (Box 7)
      - Gonzales (medical?) (Box 7)
      - "Ho, Mr." (immigration problems?) (Box 7)
      - Huang, J. (employment) (Box 7)
      - Huie, W. A. (assault) (Box 7)
      - Jain, J. (employment) (Box 7)
      - Lee, N. (assault) (Box 7)
      - Lee, S. (assault) (Box 7)
      - Mazhar, I. (employment discrimination) (Box 7)
      - Melton, K. (employment discrimination) (Box 7)
      - Patel, P. P. (employment discrimination) (Box 7)
      - Red Dragon Restaurant (discrimination?) (Box 7)
      - Saxena, R. (employment discrimination) (Box 7)
      - Schafer family (discrimination) (Box 7)
      - Tewari et al. (employment discrimination) (Box 7)
      - Tien, K. (assault) (Box 7)
      - Wei, M. (employment discrimination) (Box 7)
      - Young, W. (discrimination) (Box 7)
      - Zhou, J. (employment) (Box 7)
    - Other legal cases
      - Huang, L. G. (Massachusetts), 1985 (Box 7)
      - Isa, Esha (Illinois), 1988-89 (Box 7)
      - Loo, Jim (North Carolina), 1988-1989
        - Case ruling (Box 7)
        - Correspondence (Box 7)
        - Documents (Box 7)
        - Organizing and fundraising efforts (Box 7)
        - Probable cause hearing transcript (Box 7)
      - Lor/Yang (Minnesota), 1989-1990
        - Correspondence (Box 7)
        - Documents (Box 7)
      - Takahashi (California), 1988 (Box 7)
      - Yim, C. K. (Michigan), 1985 (Box 7)
- Topical, 1985-1994
  The Topical series (1.75 linear feet, 1985-1994) includes ACJ's topical files relating to various issues that the ACJ documented including articles and clippings on Asian-Americans, collected materials from other APA groups, documents on legislation affecting Asian-Americans as well as news articles detailing specific incidents of anti-Asian-American violence and discrimination. This series shows the kinds of issues and ideas that the ACJ wanted to track and also demonstrates the ACJ's broader aims of advocating for Asian Americans in general.
  - Articles/clippings, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Anti-Asian Violence Network, 1984-1985; 1988 (Box 8)
  - APA Leader Council, 1988 (Box 8)
  - APASO (Asian Pacific American Student Organization, Michigan State University), 1989-1990 (Box 8)
  - Asian Americans for Equality (Box 8)
  - Asian Foundation for Community Development, 1986-1989 (Box 8)
  - Asian Law Caucus, 1989-1991 (Box 8)
  - Asian Pacific Heritage Week, 1986; 1988 (Box 8)
  - Association for Asian American Studies, scattered (Box 8)
  - Battered women, 1988-1990 (Box 8)
  - Business Advisory Council, 1988 (Box 8)
  - Campus issues, 1987-1990 (Box 8)
  - Chicago Commission on Asian American Affairs, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
  - Civil Rights Act of, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Committee Against Anti-Asian Violence, 1988-1992 (Box 8)
  - Crime victim's rights, 1985; 1988 (Box 8)
  - Cultural Leadership program, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Detroit Chinatown proposal, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Detroit Ecumenical Working Group of Asian Pacific Americans (DEWGAPA), 1988-1990 (Box 8)
  - Detroit Minority Business Development Center, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
  - Discrimination, 1986-1994 (Box 8)
  - Ecumenical Working Group of Asian Pacific Americans (EWGAPA)
    - 1987 (Box 8)
    - 1988 (Box 8)
    - 1989 (Box 8)
    - 1990 (Box 8)
    - 1991 (Box 8)
    - 1992 (Box 8)
    - 1993 (Box 9)
    - 1994 (Box 9)
    - Study guide, 1988-1989 (Box 9)
  - English only statements, 1989 (Box 9)
  - English proficiency exam at Wayne State University, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Governor's Advisory Commission on Asian-American Affairs, 1985; 1987; 1991 (Box 9)
  - House Bill no. 4508 (Asian Pacific American Commission), 1993 (Box 9)
  - House Concurrent Resolution no. 147, 1989 (Box 9)
  - House Resolution no. 442 redress, 1986-1989 (Box 9)
  - House Resolution no. 2712, 1990 (Box 9)
  - International Institute of Metropolitan Detroit, 1988-1991 (Box 9)
  - Lakes Area Council for Diversity, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Michigan Department of Civil Rights, 1988-1990 (Box 9)
  - Michigan Victim Alliance, 1987-1990 (Box 9)
  - Midwest APA students, 1989-1991 (Box 9)
  - Model minority, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
  - National Asian Pacific Bar Association (NAPBA), 1989-1992 (Box 9)
  - National Congressional Conference on Asian-American Violence, November 1989 (Box 9)
  - National Network Against Asian-American Violence, 1990-1993 (Box 9)
  - Oberlin College protests, 1990 (Box 9)
  - Roland Hwang files, 1992-1994; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Slurs and stereotypes, 1988-1990 (Box 9)
  - UMASC (University of Michigan Asian Student Coalition), 1987-1990 (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan, 1987-1990 (Box 9)
  - Wayne State University beatings, 1988-1990 (Box 9)
  - WTVS, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Youth outreach, 1988-1989 (Box 9)
- Visual Materials, 1986-1996
  The Visual Materials series (0.25 linear feet and 7 digital audiovisual files, 1986-1996 and undated) contains several videotapes, including videos of the ACJ rededication dinner, videos of regional conferences and workshops that the ACJ took part in, and several videos sponsored by the ACJ that promote Asian-American awareness. The photographs are unlabeled, but appear to be from a meeting or workshop. Videotapes were digitized in 2021.
  - Photographs of meetings, etc., undated (Box 9)
  - Videotapes
    - ACJ Rededication Dinner, 1986; 2 videotapes (Box 9)
      - ACJ Rededication Dinner, Tape 1, April 12, 1986; [05100-1]; 1 videocassettes (VHS Videotape ); (American Citizens for Justice Rededication Dinner at Troy Hilton Hotel on Saturday April 12, 1986 at 7:00 PM.) (Box 9)
        (1:55:47)
      - ACJ Rededication Dinner, Tape 2, April 12, 1986; [05100-2]; 1 videocassettes (VHS Videotape ); (American Citizens for Justice Rededication Dinner at Troy Hilton Hotel on Saturday April 12, 1986 at 7:00 PM.) (Box 9)
        (6:42)
    - Asian Pacific American Conference, Lansing Community College, 1991 (Box 9)
      - Asian Pacific American Conference, Lansing Community College, Reel 1 & 2 of 4, 1 videocassettes (VHS Videotape ) (Box 9)
        - 1991 May 09, [05100-3-1]; (Introduction, Margo Lum Smith, President Mid-Michigan Asian Pacific American Association (MAPAA), adressing crowd about history and function of the MAPAA. Other speakers include Dr. M. Valeriana Moeller, Dr. Lloyd Tran, Dr. Antonio Piedo?, Dr. Jeffrey Jones? (dir. of research at Michigan Dept. of Civil Rights))
          (Duration: 01:16:45)
      - Asian Pacific American Conference, Lansing Community College, Reel 3 & 4 of 4, 1 videocassettes (VHS Videotape ) (Box 9)
        - 1991 May 09, [05100-4-1]; (Continued speakers, Dr. Dale D'Mello, Dr. Paul Y Liu. Closing Remarks with Rita Bunton, LCC.)
          (Duration: 1:15:249)
    - Solace, 1996 (Box 9)
      - Solace (Dir. Michael Sandoval), 1 videocassettes (VHS Videotape ) (Box 9)
        - 1996, [05100-5-1]; (Dramatic film with documentary-inspired monologues and liv-action fictional sequences. Racism, mysticism, slice of life, Vietnamese-Americans living in Rural America. Original recording on 16mm film. Project made possible by contributions of the ARTS Foundation of Michigan and the University of Michigan.)
          (Duration: 26:05)
    - Cultural Sensitivity Asian cultures, Rebecca Lo, undated (Box 9)
      - Cultural Sensitivity -Asian cultures- Rebecca Lo, 1 videocassettes (VHS Videotape ) (Box 9)
        - Undated, [05100-6-1]; (4-part lecture on Cultural Sensitivity and approaches for social services in Asian community in the United States. 1. Asian Culture, Historical 2. Asian-American Cultural Practices 3. Implications and Applications for Social Service Providers 4. Health Perceptions, Asian Culture in the context of acculturation (Western/Eastern Medicine) Ongoing Q & A Sessions.)
          (Duration: 01:37:50)
    - Asian-American identity (interview project sponsored by the ACJ), undated (Box 9)
      - Asian-American identity, 1 videocassettes (VHS Videotape ) (Box 9)
        - Undated, [05100-7-1]; (Interview project sponsored by the ACJ on Asian-American Identity and Experience. Produced by Charles Cheng (also main narrator) featuring student, faculty and staff interviews at Midwestern Universities - University of Michigan, Oberlin College, University of Wisconsin, University of Minnesota.)
          (Duration: 01:02:32)